Guide to the Chuck Stone Papers, 1931-2007 and undated RL.01259
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chuck Stone papers
1931-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stone, Chuck
RL.01259
36.2 Linear Feet 18,650 items
Charles Sumner (Chuck) Stone was a prominent African-American journalist, with a career spanning from his early days at the New York Age (1958-1959) to his position as editor and columnist at the Philadelphia Daily News (1972-1991). Between 1965 and 1967 he was special assistant and press secretary to New York representative Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. He served as mediator between the police and suspected criminals for over 20 years, most notably in his negotiation of the Graterford Prison hostage crisis in 1981. He is the author of multiple books, from political analyses to a novel about his time with Powell and (in 2003) a children's book. He was also an educator for many years, as Professor of English at the University of Delaware from 1985-1991 and Walter Spearman Professor of Journalism at UNC-Chapel Hill from 1991 to 2005, when he retired. The collection contains clippings, correspondence, writings, scrapbooks, photographs, video, audio, research files, and printed materials pertaining to the life and career of Chuck Stone. The papers span the years 1931-2007 and document Stone's journalism career and writings, his political career and relationship with Adam Clayton Powell, Jr., and his role as an educator.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Chuck Stone Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2004 and 2007, as part of the John Hope Franklin Center for African and African-American Documentation.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1924 July 21 Born in St. Louis, Mo. to Charles Sumner and Madalene Martha (Chafin) Stone
1942-1943 Attended Springfield College
1943 Drafted, commissioned as a navigator in the U.S. Army Air Corps
1948 Graduated from Wesleyan University, A.B. Degree in political science and economics
1951 Graduated from the University of Chicago, M.A. in sociology
1956-1958 Represented CARE ( Cooperative American Remittances Everywhere) in Egypt and India
1958 Began work as a journalist at the New York Age
1958 Oct. 4 Married Georgia Louise Davis
1960 Became Associate Director of the American Committee on Africa Became White House correspondent and editor of the Washington Afro-African
1963 Became Editor-in-Chief and Columnist for the Chicago Defender
1965 Television commentator for WCIU Chicago
1964-1967 Press secretary and special assistant for New York Congressional Representative Adam Clayton Powell, Jr.
1967 Published Tell It Like It Is
1968 Publication of Black Political Power in America
1969 Commentator for The Today Show on NBC
1970 Publication of King Strut
1970-1972 Director of Minority Services for the ETS ( Educational Testing Service)
1972-1991 Senior Editor and Columnist at the Philadelphia Daily News
1975 First president of the National Association of Black Journalists First president of the Philadelphia Association of Black Journalists
1981 Nov. Served as negotiator in the Graterford Prison hostage situation in Graterford, PA
1985 Co-founded FairTest, the National Center for Fair & Open Testing Became Professor of English at the University of Delaware
1989-1991 Attended Eastern Baptist Theological Seminary
1991 Appointed Walter Spearman Professor of Journalism and Mass Communication at UNC-Chapel Hill
1997 Served as readers' advocate for the St. Louis Post-Dispatch
2003 Published Squizzy the Black Squirrel: A Fabulous Tale of Friendship
2005 Retired from teaching
2014 April 6 Passed away in Capel Hill, NC
Collection Overview
The Chuck Stone Papers span the years 1931 to 2007. The collection consists of clippings and other print materials, correspondence, writings, scrapbooks, photographs, a videotape, research files, and diplomas and certificates pertaining to the life and career of Chuck Stone. Of the subject areas documented here are Stone's career as a prominent African-American journalist, his political career and relationship with Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. (including Powell's time as head of the Congressional Committee on Education and Labor), his role as a mediator between suspects and the criminal justice system, and his involvement in civil rights struggles in the United States. Also represented, but to a much lesser extent, is his teaching career at the University of Delaware and UNC-Chapel Hill. The collection is divided into nine series, each described below. Of these, the largest by far are the Clippings and the Subject Files series, which document respectively Stone's journalistic writings (especially during his time at the Philadelphia Daily News) and his research interests over the years, including racial politics in the U.S., African-Americans in the media, the criminal justice system, censorship and free speech, and standardized testing. The collection was acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Collection of African and African-American Documentation.
The Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. Congressional Series documents Stone's time as press secretary and special assistant to Powell. It contains office and business correspondence both to and from Stone; clippings and other printed materials about Powell or the Committee on Education and Labor; office files on individual members of congress (notably Florida Democrat Sam Gibbons, partly responsible for the campaign to remove Powell from his position as head of the Committee); files related to the workings of the Committee; press releases written by Stone; and a number of papers relating to Powell's exclusion from Congress in 1967. This series should be useful both for those interested in the career of Powell, since Stone worked for him during a pivotal time in his career, and for those interested in the workings of the Committee on Education and Labor during that time.
The Clippings Series is made up predominantly of Stone's columns from the Philadelphia Daily News and the NEA Viewpoint (a Newspaper Enterprise Association column syndicated by United Media), as well as articles about Stone from various newspapers, and some writings by Stone appearing in other newspapers. Topics addressed by Stone in his columns include racial politics in the U.S., Philadelphia politics, the media, Ireland, Stone's travels in Africa, women's issues and feminism, the criminal justice system, and standardized testing. Researchers interested in Stone's journalism career prior to 1972 will find some earlier clippings here, but should consult the Scrapbooks Series for more extensive materials and clippings from that period.
The Correspondence Series contains correspondence to and from Stone relating to business and personal matters. The majority of this series is made up of general correspondence or correspondence relating to Stone's position as editor and columnist of the Philadelphia Daily News. The remainder of the series comprises topical folders of correspondence, such as the correspondence between Stone and Edward M. Ryder, an inmate at Graterford Prison. Other such correspondence can be found in the "Criminal justice system" subsection of the Subject Files Series.
The Other Writings Series houses Stone's writings not contained in the Clippings Series, such as speeches, sermons, and television transcripts; business documents and research files pertaining to different projects on which Stone worked, such as his attempts to develop his own life or his writings on Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. into a movie, or various uncompleted book projects; and a small subset of writings by others, including an autobiography of Corinne Huff on which Stone worked. It is divided into three subseries to accommodate the restriction on the collection: the Published Writings by Stone Subseries, the Unpublished Writings by Stone Subseries, and the Writings by Others Subseries. Notably absent from this series are manuscripts of Stone's books. Instead, the series contains either shorter published materials, such as publicly delivered speeches, or working documents assembled for the creation of larger works.
The Scrapbooks Series houses the contents of four scrapbooks assembled by Stone during the 1950s and 1960s. They contain a number of clippings, programs, and some correspondence pertaining to his time at the New York Age, the Washington Afro-American, the Chicago Defender, and working for Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. The series is especially useful for documenting Stone's early career and his position as an outspoken African-American journalist and defender of civil rights. Researchers interested in this period in Stone's life should also consult the Clippings Series for more materials from the period in question that are not present in the scrapbooks.
The St. Louis Series is a small series housing clippings and correspondence related to Stone's brief position as ombudsman for the St. Louis Post-Disptach, overseeing their coverage of the 1997 mayoral election. The series is divided into a Published Materials Subseries, which houses clippings from the Post-Dispatch and related newspapers, and an Unpublished Materials Subseries, in which can be found correspondence, business documents, and responses to several readers polls conducted by Stone.
In the Subject Files Series can be found Stone's research files on different subject areas, arranged alphabetically. The files contain primarily clippings, but also some correspondence and notes. Several subcategories that are heavily represented and should be mentioned are the files on censorship and the first amendment, on the criminal justice system, on standardized testing, and on materials relating to his time at UNC-Chapel Hill. There are also numerous files related to racial politics in the U.S., but these files are less discrete than the categories described above and are to be found throughout the series rather than under a specific subheading.
The Teaching Materials Series contains a small amount of material pertaining to Stone's teaching career. The bulk of this series comes from his time at UNC-Chapel Hill, and includes syllabi, exams, assignments, student papers, and other teaching paperwork. Most heavily represented in this regard is Stone's popular class on censorship, for which there are multiple syllabi and exams from different years and semesters.
Finally, the Audiovisual Materials Series collects photographs touching on all aspects of Stone's life, from press photos of Stone and Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. to family portraits. Also included in this series are a videotape of a documentary about Powell, press passes and identification badges, and an election pin kept by Stone.
Unprocessed Addition 2009-0009 (50 items; .2 lin. ft.; dated 1963-2005) comprises primarily photographs, but also contains a few letters, clippings, awards, and a dvd-r. The original DVD-R is closed to patron use; however, the information on the disk has been migrated to the electronic records server.
Addition 2012-0099 has been processed and included in the original collection's description as boxes 64-66. Some parts of this addition have been interfiled into existing boxes.
Related Material
Those interested in Chuck Stone and his life may also wish to consult the Davis Family Papers, also housed at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, which contain materials collected by Stone's wife Louise Davis Stone pertaining to the Davis family and their activities. This collection, cataloged separately from the Chuck Stone Papers, is searchable by title in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
United States. Congress. House. Committee on Education and Labor; African Americans -- Politics and government; African Americans -- Civil rights; Mass media and race relations -- United States; Mass media and culture -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Minority journalists -- United States; Civil rights -- United States -- History -- 20th century; African Americans in mass media; Videocassettes; African American press; African Americans and mass media -- United States; Criminal justice, Administration of -- United States; African American journalists; Educational tests and measurements -- United States; Censorship -- United States -- Case studies; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Typescripts; United States -- Race relations; Speeches; Clippings (information artifacts); John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972; University of Delaware -- Faculty; Stone, Chuck; Philadelphia Daily News (Firm); University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. School of Journalism and Mass Communication -- Faculty
- Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. Congressional Series, 1959-1998 and undated, bulk 1961-1967, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series documents Stone's activities as special assistant to Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. between 1965 and 1967, and includes speeches, press releases, correspondence between Powell and Stone, correspondence to and from other political figures and other members of Powell's staff, files on specific figures and organizations, clippings about Powell, and several folders of correspondence, clippings, and business documents specific to Powell's role as chair of the Committee on Education and Labor. The folders are labelled by topic and arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Building Service Employees' Union, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Child Development Group of Mississippi, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Education and Labor, 1962, 1965-1966, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Congressional votes, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1972, bulk 1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--ACP by CSS, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Exclusion, 1967, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Federal and State Bureau of Apprenticeship and Training documents, undated (Box 1)
  - Gibbons, Sam, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Magazine articles on Powell, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Oversize magazine articles on Powell, 1964-1967 (Box 63)
  - Articles on Powell, 1967 and 1998 (Box 64)
  - New York Times editorials, 1961-1969 (Box 1)
  - Poverty programs, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Powell, Adam Clayton, Jr., 1959-1976, 1993, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Powell, Adam Clayton, Jr., 1965-1998, 11 folders (Box 3)
  - President's public papers, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Press releases, 1963-1967, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Thompson, Frank, 1972 (Box 3)
- Clippings Series, 1945-2007 and undated, 12 boxes
  Series is comprised of clippings kept by Stone. The bulk of these are Stone's columns in the Philadelphia Daily News (1972-1991) and NEA Viewpoint (1987-1995), which deal with topics such as racial politics in the U.S., Philadelphia politics, the media, Ireland, Stone's travels in Africa, women's issues and feminism, the criminal justice system, and standardized testing, among others. Also included are materials documenting Stone's early journalism career from the New York Age, New York Citizen-Call, Chicago Daily Defender, and Washington Afro-American; clippings from various sources documenting Stone's interests and research; and articles about Stone from various publications. Of interest may also be the selection of clippings from 1972-1974 from the Philadelphia Daily News that Stone made, apparently for a planned sequel to Tell it Like it Is, his 1967 book of selected columns from the Washington Afro-American. These can be found at the end of the clippings from the Daily News, under the subheading " Tellin' it Like it Oughta Be columns."
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title, then chronologically by date.
  - About Stone, 1945 Mar. 22-1991 Nov., 5 folders (Box 4)
  - About Stone, 1992 Jan. 5-2007 Mar. 29 and undated, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - About Stone--photographs of Stone in media, 1984 Feb. 19, 1992 Jan. 20 and undated (Box 5)
  - About Stone, 1960s-2000s (Box 64)
  - Articles by Stone--miscellaneous newspapers and magazines, 1971 Nov.-2000 Sept. 26 and undated (Box 5)
  - Articles by Stone--miscellaneous newspapers and magazines (Box 66)
  - Chicago Daily Defender, 1963 Aug. 15-1964 Aug. 6 and undated (Box 5)
  - Chronicle of Higher Education, 1991 Oct. 9-1998 June 5 and undated (Box 5)
  - Columns by selected journalists: Ada Louise Huxtable, Mike Ryoko, David S. Broder, Mary McGrory, George F. Will, and William Safire, 1968-1978 and undated (Box 5)
  - Collected by Stone, 2000s (Box 64)
  - Life, 1963 Nov. 29, 1992 June 1 (Box 6)
  - Mounted clipping about John Shelton Reed from the News and Observer, 1996 June 30 (Box 6)
  - NEA Viewpoint, 1987 Feb. 24-1995 Jan. 24, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - New York Age, 1958 Oct. 18, 1958 Dec. 20, 1960 Feb. 27, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - New York Citizen-Call, 1960 June 4-1960 July 23 (Box 6)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1972 Feb. 2-1973 Dec. 27, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1974 Jan. 2-1975 Sept. 26, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1975 Oct. 1-1976 Dec. 21, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1977 Jan. 4-1980 Sept. 2, 11 folders (Box 10)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1980 Sept. 9-1983 Apr. 29, 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1983 May 3-1987 Aug. 28, 11 folders (Box 12)
  - Philadelphia Daily News, 1987 Sept. 8-1991 July 12, 1993 Feb. 16, and undated, 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Philadelphia Daily News
    - Chuck Stone in Africa columns, 1978 May 18-June 17 (Box 13)
    - Columns about Ireland, 1981 Nov. 30-Dec. 4 (Box 13)
    - Columns about Philadelphia and black civic responsibility, 1981 June 30-1983 Nov. 11 (Box 13)
    - Columns about Philadelphia politicians: Bill Gray, Bill Green, and Frank Rizzo, 1978 Sept. 29-1991 May 28 (Box 13)
    - Columns about women, 1978 Sept. 22, 1987 Dec. 15-1991 Sept. 10 and undated (Box 13)
    - Readers' letters about Stone, 1978 Apr. 11, 1989 Feb. 7-Mar. 3 (Box 13)
  - Philadelphia Daily News (Box 14)
    - Tellin' it Like it Oughta Be columns, 1972 Mar. 21-1974 Aug. 9, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Philadelphia Inquirer series on police brutality, 1977 Apr. 24-27 (Box 15)
  - Stone's Journal, 1978 May-1980 Apr. (Box 15)
  - Urban Journalism Workshop Newspapers, 1978 July 20-1991 July 19 (Box 15)
  - Various Newspapers, 1980 Mar. 28-1996 May 20 (Box 15)
  - Washington Afro-American, 1961 Dec. 2-1963 May 18 and undated (Box 15)
- Correspondence Series, 1961-2005 and undated, 5 boxes
  Contains Stone's correspondence from the 1960s to 2005. In keeping with Stone's original arrangement, some folders are categorized by topic, while others simply house general correspondence within a particular span of years.
  Of particular interest in the topical folders is the correspondence relating to black political power in America (the topic, not only Stone's book of the same title) and the correspondence with Edward M. Ryder, an inmate at the State Correctional Facility at Graterford, PA from 1973-1993. Also to be found are two folders of correspondence from a number of individuals related to Stone's role as negotiator in the hostage crisis at Graterford in 1981.
  The bulk of the remainder of the series is made up of two categories. One is simply general correspondence. These folders contain correspondence from such figures as Martin Luther King, Jr., Jackie Robinson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Barry Goldwater, LeRoi Jones, Edward Kennedy, and others, along with family correspondence and business correspondence both to and from Stone from the 1960s to the 2000s. The other is correspondence specific to Stone's position as editor and columnist at the Philadelphia Daily News, which includes internal memos and letters with other staff members, letters from readers, and business letters relevant to his position at the newspaper. Researchers should be aware that these appear to be rough categorizations on Stone's part, and that there are a few letters specific to his role at the Philadelphia Daily News in the general correspondence folders, and some general business correspondence in the Philadelphia Daily News folders.
  It should also be noted that correspondence on particular topics can also be found in relevant series. For instance, correspondence with or relating to Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. is to be found in that series. Researchers interested in Stone's role with the Graterford crisis and his correspondence with prison inmates should also consult the Criminal justice system files in the Subject Files Series.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Black political power in America, 1967-1969 (Box 16)
  - Collegiality, 1992-1995 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence from Krishna Stone [daughter], 1978-1988, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Correspondence with Edward M. Ryder, 1978-1987 (Box 16)
  - General correspondence, 1961-2005 and undated, 20 folders (Box 16-18)
  - Hostages-related correspondence, 1981, 1985, 1987, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Philadelphia Daily News correspondence, 1972-1987, 15 folders (Box 19-20)
  - Thank-you notes from students, 1992-1999 (Box 20)
  - General correspondence (Box 66)
  - Philadelphia Daily News congratulations, 1979 (Box 66)
- Other Writings Series, 1931-2003 and undated, bulk 1963-2003, 4 boxes
  Comprised of materials relating to writing and other media projects beyond the columns found in the Clippings Series. It is divided into three subseries: Published Writings by Stone, Unpublished Writings by Stone, and Writings by Others. Detailed series descriptions follow below.
  - Published Writings by Stone Subseries, 1963-2003 and undated, 2 boxes
    Contains speeches, sermons, and transcripts of television broadcasts (on WCIU Chicago) by Stone.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Article drafts, 2000 (Box 21)
    - Media speeches, 1980s, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Sermons, 1981-1997 and undated (Box 21)
    - Speeches, 1963-1994 and undated, 7 folders (Box 21)
    - Speeches, 1994-2003 and undated, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Speeches--NAACP, 1983, 1986 (Box 22)
    - WCIU transcripts, 1965 (Box 22)
    - Squizzy the Black Squirrel (Box 66)
  - Unpublished Writings by Stone Subseries, 1931-1998 and undated, bulk 1967-1998, 2 boxes
    Houses unpublished writings by Stone, such as an introduction written for the unpublished volume The Poetry of the Black Revolution, as well as documentation of other projects undertaken by Stone, ranging from book and syndication contracts to research files set aside for use in several uncompleted works, such as Free Speech and Jealous Mistresses and, with Dennis Jackson, Mass Communication Law in Delaware. Also found here are manuscripts of various movie or stage adaptations of Stone's novelization of his time with Adam Clayton Powell, Jr., as well as business documents relating to his attempts to secure a movie deal.
    - Book contracts, 1967-1976 (Box 23)
    - Eastern Baptist Theological Seminary writings, 1991 (Box 23)
    - Free Speech and Jealous Mistresses
      - Case folders, undated (Box 23)
      - Research files, 1931-1991 and undated, 3 folders (Box 23)
      - Scholarly Resources, Inc. correspondence and documents, 1987, 1998 (Box 23)
    - Introduction to The Poetry of the Black Revolution, undated (Box 23)
    - King Strut
      - Screen treatment and correspondence, 1970-1991 (Box 23)
    - Mass Communication Law in Delaware
      - Research and correspondence, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 23)